[music]
[Harrison] Here we are in the big cypress.
[Peter] The Everglades
most people don't go to, right?
-Yes, yes.
What I really want to
tap into today, Harrison,
is we have this beautiful nature.
It's way bigger of a scale
than most people know.
Yes.
And there are few people
that have sort of made a life out here.
Made the cypress their life
and actually, you know,
the designation
of the cypress as a preserve
is a big part of the history
and why the people are here.
Because when the park,
when Everglades National Park,
became a national park in 1947,
hunting and any commercial use
of the land was outlawed.
And obviously with all the good
that came of that,
there was also the bad and the people
that couldn't live off the land anymore.
Whereas the big cypress,
it's still preserved that way.
People can still hunt and use the land,
the Natives who live here, and we're
going to meet today still use it that way.
And when you go Google Earth here,
put the blue line street view on…
None.
South Florida, in this area,
you see nothing.
Nothing.
-It looks like the West.
-Yes.
Like Montana or Arizona or something.
Something like that, and if you told
a bunch of people in Dade County,
oh, you know, you can drive dirt roads.
They're like, "I've never been
on a dirt road in my life."
The reason that these trails are like this,
this is actually from when
they tried to sabotage the place
before it was designated as a preserve.
The lumber companies came in here
and were cutting.
So all these old trails
are just remnants of that.
[Peter] Let's see if we can get into this.
[Harrison] It was only
a matter of time, huh?
Look, remnants of a coral reef when
Florida, and this part was all underwater
before the last ice age.
You're like in the jungle,
and you can start to see here
why they call this
the Amazon of the Americas.
Look at that.
[Peter] There's people out here
that have lived their whole lives.
-Different subculture.
-Whole lives. Yes.
These people have been here
for generations.
Don't know much about Copeland,
but let's explore.
We're literally inside of the Cypress
and all these people who live here.
You might expect to see
a panther in their yard.
-A Florida panther.
Oh, can you stop here?
I'm going to ask this guy.
Morning, sir.
You see any Florida panthers out here?
-No panthers lately.
Lot of bear.
-A lot of bear?
We're making a video on the whole area.
I just wanted to talk to locals.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I've been down here since 1965.
-How many people
live out here in this community?
-Well, I'd say about 250.
-250?
E'rybody know everyone.
-And it's pretty nice?
-Pretty nice.
That's cool. What's your name?
-Billy.
-Billy, Peter.
-Pleased to meet you, sir.
-Yeah, nice to meet you.
-Harrison.
-Pleased to meet you.
[Billy] This town was a work camp.
This was a logging camp.
-Logging camp?
-Yeah.
Back in the '20s,
'27, 1900, 1800 something.
They just cut all the cypress
out of this camp.
-Okay.
You know white lightning and all that.
The drug smuggling and all that.
They made a movie out there.
Do you remember that back in the day here,
the drug smuggling?
Yeah.
-Big time?
-Big time.
What was it?
It was everything they can get
from cross from Columbia.
Start by offshore, about 35 miles offshore.
And unload the mothership into the boat,
the cigar boat bring in.
-When was that happening?
It happened for a long time.
I was catching mullets.
I was mullet fishing.
-Oh, cool.
Yeah.
We made plenty of money off of mullet.
I didn't know what they were doing.
Didn't matter to me
'cause it was none of my business.
-So a lot of people were making
a lot of money out here with the smuggling?
Yeah. A lot of people.
It wasn't a locals.
It was people out of town.
-Oh, okay.
It was people out of town
making all that money.
The local had made no money.
The local had to sit back and look.
[Peter] That's interesting.
So this was a lumber town.
It's peaceful, I gotta say. It's sorta…
-You wanna rip off and be away from it all.
-Yeah.
It's just the camera's not gonna capture,
you guys, unfortunately.
But the buffer zone
around here is absolutely massive.
So this is in a way preserved
because it's surrounded by these parks.
Yes. Yeah.
There's no development
that's gonna happen out here.
I would've liked to ask Billy
if he thinks as a resident…
-…if they're ever gonna overtake this.
-[man speaking outside]
What's that?
-…a live video.
We're making a video looking for Panthers.
-You ain't gonna see one right now, bro.
-No?
-I watch you all the time on YouTube, man.
-Are you serious?
-Stop it, bro.
-Stop it. You stop it. You stop it.
Man, that's what's up.
I do, bro.
-You cool with me rolling the camera?
-That's what's up, bro.
-I see you all the time, man.
-What are you doing out here?
-I live right here, bro.
-In the tent?
-Yes, sir.
-What's your name?
-I'm Brian.
-Brian.
-Yes, sir.
-How'd you end up out here?
-My whole life, bro. My family.
-Seriously?
-Seriously.
I got another guy you'd probably be
interested in talking to is my uncle.
He's a wiz, man.
He knows all about this stuff, man.
-Can we talk to wiz man?
-Yeah, let's go.
Let's go talk to wiz man.
Cool, man.
We were just sitting there
talking and stuff.
And a Panther just come right
on his little dock, you know?
Probably from here to the car away from us.
A young one.
And I was like what's up with that, man?
He's like, he's been coming out
pretty recent, man. You know?
And pretty regular.
I'm like, no sh*t, you know?
So we're really not allowed
to feed him and stuff, so…
-How are the dogs doing with the Panthers?
-You know, we look at them.
Oh, they get at each other.
The Panthers don't really bother them.
He likes the little things,
the cats and the chickens.
But… They're pretty cool, man.
That's crazy, bro.
-I appreciate it.
-Yeah, man. That's pretty cool, man.
So if I came here on my own,
I might have had a different response.
Oh, yeah. Nah.
It's a joke.
Hey, Uncle Scott.
You never know
what you're going to get into.
-Sleeping?
-I'm trying to.
Alright, sorry about that.
I'll see you after while, Unc.
We just talked to Billy.
-The old Black guy?
-Yeah.
Yeah, he's awesome, man.
Good guy.
So, living out here.
-Yes, sir.
-Separated from the world feeling.
Basically, it is a little different.
I mean, you got, seems
a little more freedom, maybe, I should say.
You know, you don't really get bothered
by many people unless you act a fool.
I mean, it's freedom, bro.
What you see is what it is.
-Alright.
-Everybody knows everybody.
It reminds me of the old days, you know?
Where you can go to your neighbor
and borrow an egg.
Nowadays you go to the city, they'll shut
the door on you and won't answer.
A little different.
But, yeah, man, it's pretty cool.
I'd like to take you guys somewhere
and show you more.
I'm going to close this gate here.
My uncle's gate.
And then I'm going to go find my brother
and we're going to show
you some good videos.
-Where's your brother?
-He's right across the way.
We're going to follow you.
-Let's go.
-Okay. Okay.
[Brian calling out]
[Brian] He wants to know about
the woods and all that sh*t, man.
-How are you doing, sir?
-He's good f*cking people, man.
I watch him on YouTube all the time.
[Peter] How are you doing?
-What's your name?
-Vince. Vincent Brown.
Vince, yeah, Peter.
-He's good people.
-So Vince, you grew up out here.
-Yeah.
Small town sh*t, you know?
-Small town sh*t?
What about the animals?
-Bears and panthers.
-Bears.
Well, we had a bear attack
a little while back.
-An attack?
Yeah, I got a bear in a guy's house
and took him out of it. An old man.
-The 89 year old man.
-Do you remember that?
I don't know if the old man was feeding
the bear or not or what was going on.
You know what I mean?
That's the worst thing
you can do is feed one.
You know what I mean? Feed anything.
If you don't want it around, don't feed it.
-[Brian] I'm going to have him bring one.
-[Peter] What?
A python.
[Peter] He's bringing a python? [giggles]
I want to see a python.
Did you know about this place, Harrison?
I knew about Copeland.
I didn't know that we would be able to
meet so many friends here.
-You told me Totch was your uncle.
-Yeah.
I had been… Totch's book is my favorite
book I've ever read, hands down.
-I know that sounds crazy, but…
-[Peter] Who's Totch?
Totch was a Chokoloskee legend.
He was born in 1920. He died in 1996.
He was a fisherman.
He was a Medal of Honor recipient.
-[Vince] Yeah. Smuggler.
-Smuggler. He lived off the land.
I mean, a true polymath
of this corner of the world.
-Gator hunter.
-Gator hunter. All of it.
That's probably the biggest thing he did.
I love the way his book
was written in black and white.
Like, this happened,
this happened, this happened.
So you know there was nothing
but just facts.
Yeah.
And the way he approached life
with this fearlessness
and then this love for the openness,
just deeply resonates with me.
Totch was one of the true pioneers
of the modern day out here.
Yeah, he was definitely
a pioneer of everybody.
Yeah, and his family too.
So he got into the smuggling big time?
Yeah. Yeah, he's got us…
He got my dad into it.
-Yeah.
-That was huge out here?
Yeah, in the '80s.
In the late '70s and '80s.
-'83 was a blockade, right?
-Yeah, smuggling marijuana on shrimp boats.
[Peter] Where was
the marijuana coming from?
Mostly Columbia, but Jamaica.
Then coming right off the shore here?
Yeah, it come right off shore here
and then we'd get there
with, call 'em the go-fast boats.
Like 24 foot Morgans
with two engines on them.
Go out there and get them
and bring them up creeks and
put it on vans
and take it down the highway.
I was like 14, 15 years old when all this
was going on. You know, I was just a kid.
I started smoking pot.
It was just fun.
We had all the money we wanted.
You know what I mean?
We just had anything we wanted.
We wanted a new motorcycle or something,
just went and got it.
It was just…
And then we run out of money, we're all
sitting there like, oh, God. [laughs]
-What's the replacement economy out here?
There's nothing really.
Nothing. You go back fishing.
[Peter] Okay, so they said
come to the backside of this house.
Yeah, it looks like a compound in here.
[Harrison] "Stay out of  my truck."
"Ain't nothing that a beer can't fix."
Well guys, we're far out there.
We're going to get back
to the nature though.
-Yes.
But look, this is an interesting
part of the state, the country,
the world.
[Peter] Oh my God.
They didn't want to come out.
It's cold. I left the female in there.
[Peter] Okay, so what do you do
with the snakes, Wayne?
I've had these guys since they were babies.
Okay, you just like…
they're pets for you.
Oh yeah.
Come here. This one I named Stripe
'cause of the long stripe.
This one here is a dwarf.
I got him from the neighbor.
He wasn't taking care of it. Ten bucks.
I finally talked him out of it
for ten dollars.
-Pythons?
-Yeah, these are ball pythons.
Ball pythons. How big do they get?
They only get up six foot.
This one's full grown.
I got them in a big 150 gallon
aquarium with logs and everything else,
and a waterfall and all that in there.
It's not easy to get these.
-Have you lived out here your whole life?
-I've been here 37 years.
But I grew up out in the Everglades.
-You love it?
-I love it. I've been here all my life.
I'm 69 years old right now.
-Why do you love it?
It's because I'm away from
all the crazy people in town.
I hate town. [laughs]
[laughing] Here, put it on him.
I'm good, Wayne.
Just want a shot with me and you.
-And snakes.
-There you go.
-There we go.
-Here.
Come here, look. Let's get them over here.
I'm getting him closer.
-That's as close as he's gonna go.
-That's about as close…
-[laughter]
I didn't start it with him.
[country music]
[Harrison] We're on Tamiami Trail now,
which connects Miami to Tampa.
This was built in 1927.
It was the first road
that came through out here.
-It's like the Savannah
a little bit, right?
Right. No, for sure.
I always tell people, if you took a picture
of that in the right light,
and you told somebody you were in Africa,
they might just believe you.
-Yeah.
Just missing the lions, you know?
Oh, a big alligator right there.
-You want to go look?
-Oh, yeah. Let's do it.
[Peter] There's one sunbathing.
Cold night last night.
I think lower 40s here.
It's warming up.
This guy getting some sun.
And so I guess
they're all along these banks.
-Pretty cool.
I just noticed actually, look.
He's missing the back part of his tail.
-Oh, yeah. Right.
I don't know if
the camera's going to catch it, but…
Yeah, he lost a tail.
-Must be a good war story.
[Harrison] The smallest
post office in America, in Ochopee.
[Peter] Okay, yeah, it is. For sure.
Here we go, guys.
I've seen a lot of small ones
out in the desert west.
Utah, Arizona, but this wins.
Look at this place.
It's like an outhouse.
Ochopee Post Office.
"Considered to be the smallest post office
in the United States.
This building was formerly
an irrigation pipe shed
belonging to the JT Guant
Company tomato farm."
Okay, so they did tomatoes down here.
Hey, how you doing, sir?
Not bad. Not bad.
-That's cool.
-Smallest one around.
You're a US postal worker.
I really am.
Oh, that's cool, Donald.
Can I poke the camera
to show what this office is like?
Check it out. It's a cool little spot
to check out. Heck yeah.
Lot of little knick-knacks in here.
-Oh, that's cool.
People given me over the years
'cause it's such a tiny little thing.
-How many people have a P.O. box here?
-Nobody.
-Nobody?
Nobody has a P.O. box here.
It's all street delivery.
We have a carrier out of here.
It's a big area, too.
It's not just, like, right around here
where you see a couple buildings.
I mean, we go, like,
50-something miles that way.
-Okay.
We go down to the light
and then out, like, 20 miles.
So, it's like a 140-mile round trip
every day for the carrier.
-Oh, that's cool.
-Yeah, yeah.
It's a long gig.
But it's pretty nice out here.
You can't beat…
-Hey, how are you?
-How are you?
Remind me your name?
My name is Lisa.
Lisa, it's great to see you. Look at this
beautiful day we're having.
-Lisa, what's the fun fact of the day?
Fun fact is, I don't care.
There it is, people.
I like your customer service.
You got to write the rules.
Oh, this is cool. Look at this.
-So…
-What a place.
All the history and look,
you have all the different fresh water.
There we go.
-Lisa, you want to show him
how you do a backflip?
I'mma tell you what, I can do it.
-No, seriously.
-Seriously?
I don't want to get in trouble, though.
-Hester made a complaint.
-You did it on Saturday.
[scoffs]
[Peter] You did the backflip?
The biker that asked me to do it,
he brings groups of people.
So, one day,
they're all sitting out on the patio.
Must be 25, 30 of them.
And I did it, and they all loved it.
So, now, every time he comes in here…
I try to sneak one in
every once in a while.
I have a little over a month.
Somewhere around March 10th,
I'm going to be a great-grandmother.
-Wow.
-I turned 60 on Veterans Day, 11-11.
And I wanted to be a great-grandmother
by the time I was 60 and I got my wish.
-I'll be a great-grandmother…
-Congrats.
Somewhere around March 10th.
What's the math on that?
-What do you mean on what?
-[Peter laughs]
When did you have your first kid?
I had my first child
the day I turned 15 and a half.
Wow.
I have two kids.
I had the second one when I was 31.
We're just rambling now waiting for you.
-My hands are freezing.
-It's great to see you.
-Terry. Nice to meet you.
-Nice to meet you.
-Thank you, Lisa.
-Absolutely.
This is your restaurant?
Yes, it was my mom's.
-It was your mom's?
-Yes, she started it.
-Oh, very cool.
-I can't take that credit.
This is Gator Joe. He passed away,
but he used to sit out on the porch
and tell stories of the Everglades.
And he would have his panther out there.
And he'd jump right back in the canal
and fight an alligator.
-Out of the back side of the restaurant?
-Yes.
-Gator Joe.
-It didn't matter. Look at him right there.
He's got a cigarette between his hands
and a stick and he's in the woods.
Ochopee used to be the dream town to be
back in the day.
-It was going to be bigger than Naples.
-Really?
There was a time out here
where there were more people living
back in the early 1900s than Naples.
-So Terry, from my understanding,
you can't really develop
out in these parts too easily.
So there are only a few places?
Only what's existing.
-Only what's existing?
-You can't buy property and build anything.
This is the Big Cyprus National Park.
Big Cyprus and then we have
Everglades National Park.
-Nobody's building there.
-No.
-So you're like in this oasis.
-I am.
Of nature in a crowded state.
Absolutely.
My great grandfather
and grandfather on my mother's side
came out here and bought property
out in Everglades City.
And we have been coming out
since we were babies.
Eventually my mom said,
"Okay, this is enough.
I'm done with Miami.
Carl, we're going to the Glades."
And they bought this in the early '70s.
My dad was a mechanic,
so he had a gas station
and he was the mechanic out here.
-So other than
your business there, Joanie's ,
things are sort of going downhill
as far as businesses, that sort of thing?
-Or what's the story out here?
-There are no businesses really out here.
Yeah, okay.
This closed up many years ago
when my mom had to pull up all the tanks.
She couldn't afford it. She had to
get a loan to pull out six huge tanks.
You know, when they were doing that
all back about 30 years ago.
-Oh, when they had to change the tanks.
-Yes, yes.
So it never reopened.
And we are now
in the process of trying to
take care of it and restore it.
Okay.
So we don't lose it because if you lose
the building, you can't rebuild it.
-Those are the rules out here?
-Yeah, you can't rebuild anything.
This is original.
We want to take care of it. Just like that.
That's a, you know, work in progress.
Always, it's a hundred years old.
-You got your own world out here.
-We do.
-So when you think Miami, St. Peters…
-You can keep Miami.
Okay.
-[Harrison] Where were you born?
-I was born in Hialeah.
-Okay.
-But Hialeah had cows then.
Okay. Right, right.
I mean, it's not like that now.
[Spanish]
-Okay, you're Cuban descent?
-Si.
-I am good old American Gringo.
-Gringo.
Yeah, but you heard that.
Your accent sounds good.
But I moved to Europe
when I was a young girl
in Spain, in the Basque country.
-Oh, okay.
-And I learned Spanish there.
And my Spanish is… I don't know.
-You have a lisp?
-A little more eloquent.
-You have a little lisp.
-It's Castillian.
-Yeah, sure. Okay.
-So you've seen a lot of the world.
-Yes. Well…
How is… Why come back to this?
People would think,
why live in the middle of a hot swamp?
-[Harrison] That's the question.
-Oh.
When you figure that one out… [laughs]
Because there is
no place like this on Earth.
-There really is not.
-How so?
It's just quaint. It's beautiful.
It's rough. It's raw.
A lot of people,
including myself until recently,
didn't know that Florida
was such a frontier.
Everyone thinks West.
-I know.
-Everyone thinks Western migration, right?
But Florida was actually the last.
It was after California.
Let me tell you something.
When I was reading A Land Remembered,
I thought… cowboys?
Tough out West?
No, you are not tough until you have
roughed the swamps
in a hurricane, tying yourself to a tree.
'Cause you don't know a hurricane's coming.
They didn't know when
the bad weather was coming.
They'd be moving cattle
through the swamps with mosquitoes and
all that…
All those clothes. Women included, eh?
[Peter] What do we got here,
Harrison?
So, this is a whole soft shell crab.
The whole with shell on,
fried it in the sandwich.
-Super fresh.
-[Lisa] What do you think, guys?
-I'm starting right now, Lisa..
-You're gonna love it.
Tell them about that soft shell crab.
I'm going to take something that ain't
nothing but good. Nice and crunchy.
Good. We batter it real good
but the batter's not thick.
-Okay.
-You can't pull it off.
But you talk about good.
Mm-mm.
I always suggest to people
that you get one soft shell sandwich
and one crab cake sandwich.
Then you cut them in half
and holler, "Switch."
-Switcharoo.
-Next time.
-All right, Harrison.
-What do you think, first bite analysis?
-Mmm.
-Decent.
This is fantastic.
This is really good.
Excellent meat. The bun is good. Very soft.
Yeah. No. It's the real deal.
Yeah, look at that.
-Grouper, right?
-Grouper, yeah.
-Blackened.
-Blackened right out of the Gulf.
Delicious. About as good and tasty
as a fish as you can get.
[country music]
[Peter] What are we coming up on?
[Harrison] Clyde Butcher's gallery.
Legendary photographer
known all over the world.
So gallery out in the middle
of the Everglades?
-Yes. A photo gallery.
And not just some photos, but the best…
Hey look, there's Clyde as a mailbox.
The best kind.
So we'll get in there now and we'll delve.
[music continues]
-John, you work here at the gallery?
-That is correct.
-Okay.
-I'm an environmentalist.
I've been doing a lot of backpack
and hiking here for 35 years.
Out here, it's a deciduous coniferous.
So the trees are not dead.
They've lost their needles.
-We're going to get out there too, right?
You are going to go out there
and I'm going to show you a vision.
If you had a time machine
and brought it back 12 to 13,000 years ago,
the ocean would be over here.
We'd be a hundred miles wider.
-Okay?
-Okay.
So we have been like this
for about 8,000 years
with the vegetation types that we have.
-South Florida, Miami's over here.
-Correct.
And this is what we looked like before
people as far as Caucasians got involved.
Up here is Orlando.
And this is Kissimmee River
filling the lake from here to here
is a hundred miles.
The water was so slow
from 14 feet of sea level to nothing,
it took a year to make the journey.
And these islands right here
are mountains,
which are called hammocks,
about a meter tall.
And then you've got bay heads
with their kinds of plants
and then the prairies.
And then what you have
are pinelands where Miama is now.
-And you've got cypress tree.
-Miama?
Miama is what the old timers…
If you were to read Land Remembered
and you talked to an old timer
and you said Miami, they'd be pissed off.
But if you said…
Edit that.
But if you presented
this to somebody and you said Miama,
they'll smile and be happy with you.
Isn't it the Miami Indians?
No. Well,
Miami's in Ohio.
Miama is what
the old timers called it here.
Okay, gotcha.
-Okay, so this is the old version.
Correct. This is current.
-Okay, here we go.
-And they couldn't grow any crops.
This is all cropland.
1926, a hurricane came up here,
blue water killed 300.
1928, another unknown hurricane.
It came up here, Cat 5,
and it killed about 2,500 people.
So they built a dyke around this,
and instead of the water coming here,
it comes through here.
-And the St. Lucie Canal.
-Oh, I gotcha.
Okay.
So, this area here
was proposed as a national park
by Ernest Coe,
the father of the Everglades.
And when he proposed it,
they thought he was insane.
So he brought 'em down,
put him in the Goodyear blimp,
flew them over the proposed area,
and they were so enamored
by it in the '20s.
But there was no money in the 1930s.
We had the Depression.
Congress okayed it in '34,
but it wasn't until 1947
became a park
because of plants and animals.
And no one had ever done that before.
Brand new.
This out here are mines.
They couldn't grow crops there.
The crops would not grow.
They were absent nutrients.
And this is one of the hints.
And those are phosphate mines.
And the other problem is
we were shy on nitrogen.
So when they added
phosphate and nitrogen,
they could grow their plants,
but it impacted the rest of us.
The rain system that used to be
is now different.
We're canal driven primarily.
And Highway 41 and I-75 are dams.
-And we're right around here?
-We are here, correct.
Okay.
And this is the jet port.
Now when Ernest Coe didn't want to come
to Everglades City
for the dedication in 1947 in December,
because they had cut chunks
of what the proposed park was.
This is just a mere…
This is what… We get the leftovers
of whatever's above us.
But if we got the water here
that's been enriched
because of phosphate and nitrate,
it would kill us.
So there are areas out here
that they've been trying to
have settling dams, pretty much.
Areas, and you can have plants
that can extract the phosphate and nitrate.
What I want to show you here
is the reason this happened
got cut back is because of greed.
And then Coe wasn't gonna come
to this dedication.
But later on,
we did this.
This is what happened.
This is why we have
the Big Cypress Preserve is this.
This area here is the jet port.
It was a training jet port between
Miami-Dade
or Miama-Dade and Collier County.
And this is going to have a city of 10 to
100,000 people and that's why Leon's here.
Because he was buying land in swampland.
-Who's Leon?
-Leon that originally owned this.
-Okay, this property here.
-Yeah.
The buildings are all on land
that he had a footprint on.
[Peter] Okay.
-So Clyde Butcher…
-Clyde Butcher.
Who came out here when?
Just before Hurricane Andrew.
-When was that?
-'92.
-'92, correct.
-Okay.
They bought it from Leon
who had bought land
because he was speculating
that he would make a mint.
with all the people that were going to live
in this area because of the jet port.
When Clyde and Nicky came out here,
they said, man, you're nuts.
You think you can build a gallery out here?
They said, you must have
a loose screw somewhere.
And there's loose screw sanctuary.
So he was being investigated because
a lot of drugs ran through the area.
And they assumed
he was doing something illegal.
-Oh.
And they found out over the years that,
no, he was perfectly legal
and he was perfectly sane.
And he's won many awards
from Ansel Adams to national recognition
for the work he has done in showing
this environment that is so foreign
that most people
will stand on the outside looking in.
But I have the privilege of taking people
into it to show them what it offers.
-Okay.
And what it offers is quiet
where you can just take a breath
and listen to nothing.
You put away all your cell phones.
But with me and others,
Scott and Connie and Trish, we do walks.
You have to live in the moment.
Each step determines
whether you're successful or not.
And some of the people I've worked with
are very good at tactile walking.
They can feel things.
Others, not so much.
If you get distracted,
you end up falling in
and I grade you by your splash.
If you make a big splash,
you get less points.
I want a clean entry.
We have alligators here that tolerate us.
They've known us for years and we don't
harass them and we respect them.
So when we get by them, we speak quietly.
-Okay.
Mama's got baby gators over here.
And everything eats baby alligators.
And if the baby alligators are in trouble,
they call mom.
[imitates gator grunting sound]
And she'll come and she'll protect them.
Usually male alligators eat them,
but she has a relationship
with the male alligator here
where she actually would guide him away
from the babies over the years.
And then finally last year
she was letting them lay on his back.
Okay.
So alligators have different personalities.
Just to let you know.
-So this one…
-We're going to go see this one.
I'm going to respect her.
If I see her, I'll show you.
I'll talk quietly.
And if we see the babies, it'll be special.
Lot of times,
this is where it's rented up here.
This is where Clyde and Niki used to live.
And now they rent it out.
And when you do,
you get a visual of a morning.
I call this mental floss.
You get your brain cleared
because of all the garbage
you put up with two-legged animals.
The snakes and the gators are cool.
As long as you're away from the ones
that have been fed by people by the road.
They're dangerous.
And you can't move…
A fed gator is a dead gator.
So you never feed them
because it becomes a problem.
So what's going to happen?
I'm going to go over here quietly
and we're going to see
if Mama's there and her babies.
[whispers] There's Mama.
She's pointed this direction in the water.
[Peter whispers] Oh yeah.
Her babies may be by.
I'm not going to get in her space.
But that's where she is
and this is where she had her nest.
Last year she had a nest up in trees,
but it got raided by a bear.
This is where her nest is this year.
And this is an alligator egg.
And I'd never approached this if she was
nearby here. That's an alligator egg.
And when the eggs are laid,
the sex hasn't been determined.
What determines the sex of the alligator
is the temperature of the nest.
It's the opposite
of what happens with turtles.
So sea turtles are now being hatched
that are mostly female.
Which the question comes in 30, 40 years,
it's not going to be
are there going to be
males to fertilize them?
So you'd assume that's this way.
But in this reptile, for alligators,
the warm eggs become males, not females.
What about this water?
You said it's actually very clean.
We're in the dry season.
It is brown because of tannic acid
when the leaves decay.
But it's very clean?
Incredibly clean. We're gonna have
the different senses
and you're going to find out
how clean it is.
[splashing]
This has been trod upon
to the point that it's…
-Oh, it's cold.
-Oh, well, it's brisk.
Yeah.
If you feel warm,
it's either you're hypothermic
or somebody urinated by you.
[laughter]
[Harrison] I think the water is nice.
-It's incredible.
-Yeah.
I didn't think it would be so clean.
Of course not.
See, because you came with baggage.
You came with the ideas
of what this would represent.
[Peter] Swamp baggage?
This actually turns out,
it is called Ladies of the Night.
It's a Leon Orchid.
It has smell only at night.
And that's to attract the pollinators,
which are moths.
This is another orchid right here.
And if you touch it,
it's called Epidendrum Rigidum.
It's a rigid orchid.
-Oh, yeah.
-Very tactile, right?
-Yeah.
All this is food that's on the orchid.
This is a pond apple tree.
Around Lake Okeechobee, the pond
apples were seven, eight feet diameter.
They were huge.
-So Clyde and Nicky bought the land.
-Mm-hmm.
-But they'd been all over the world, right?
-Correct.
Lived many places around the US.
And why'd they decide on here?
There are different ways of healing.
They had lost their son to a drunk driver.
Okay.
And when they were searching
to how to sort their life out,
they came here and they
found a place that was quiet
and away from the populace.
And they felt the calmness and the beauty
of what they were experiencing.
So when they came in here and opened up
their photography opportunity
and it started getting popular,
then they realized
that this is something to be shared.
And we have a sixth grade program
that we do.
And I help with the fundraiser
and the people that come here
pay money to go on swamp walks
on any particular day when Clyde is here.
And then the money this year,
they made $40,000
from the environmental
education program.
So any sixth grader
in Collier County
can go on a swamp walk
because of the monies that are made.
You are seeing this at a point in time.
You know a picture captures the moment
and it may never be seen again.
But what we're gonna have a problem with
is within 20 years
it is going to look a lot different.
This particular tree will be gone,
this species.
-How do you know?
Because there is something
called the ash borer
that is eating the ash trees
in the Midwest.
And as it moves down here,
it is going to consume this.
This is what we find the predominance
of our orchid species on, on ash trees.
So you are seeing this now as it is,
it is going to be different.
It is spongier because
it hasn't been destroyed
by thousands of feet.
-Yeah, right?
Now we're coming up to the hat rack turn.
[Peter] Much different zone out here.
What do you feel when you came here?
You felt the sponge?
Number two, you felt the heat?
-Mm-hmm.
And what you also see is
the trees are smaller.
Then I ask people why are
these smaller trees out here?
These, many of these are just as old
as the big ones we saw.
-What makes this different?
-Less moisture?
Less moisture, less nutrients.
So this is gonna be completely crunchy dry.
And this material here that looks lumpy
and uninteresting
is the most important aspect to the health
of the Everglades right here.
If you smell it, it smells so clean,
it's going to blow your mind.
-Oh, yeah.
-It's not stinky swamp.
And that periphyton has over 300 kinds
of algae in it
that are green algae.
They produce oxygen and they are food
for a major animal out here.
[Peter] Crush it and smell it?
[John] Smell that.
Oh, yeah.
You know what?
It's called lemon bacopa.
Why is it important?
You smear it on yourself.
No, not this one. Smell that one.
I talk to the plants that I don't want to,
you know, I just
use permission from them.
This is something you also be…
That is a mosquito repellent.
-Oh, cool.
-Okay.
This one also is a mosquito eater.
It's called bladderwort.
And the little bladders that are in here
will suck in insects
and use it as nitrogen.
[John] I want you to see
a big cypress tree.
-You want to see a big cypress tree?
-Yeah.
I'll show you one of my beauties.
Now, tactile walking,
you're taking your time.
There are things under the water
you can't see.
Things under the water you can't see.
You can feel it.
Trust your gut is telling you.
I don't know if the camera
is catching this.
It's not fully, obviously, but,
it is a totally different universe in here.
-You know what, John?
-Sure.
You said you lived in the desert
for a little bit.
-I did.
-First impressions, the desert…
a lot of people think, yeah,
there's not much here, right?
It's the desert.
You give it time. You feel its rhythms.
You see the trickles of water
between the…
The ravines.
It opens up.
And I feel like the swamp
is the same.
You might drive through and say,
"Hey, there's not much here."
And then once you go granular,
it starts getting very interesting.
-Yeah.
This tree represents wisdom.
It has stood the test of time for hundreds,
maybe a thousand… or hundreds of years.
Look at this.
This just screams how beautiful this is.
Again, the water level would be here,
but this cypress has experienced a lot.
And it's in the middle…
So a dome is very stable.
So when winds blow over here,
they hold each other together.
This is one of my trees.
Others have their trees
they find particularly attractive.
But I just like the size
and I'd like you guys to stand next to it.
And give me a cell and I'll take a picture
or whatever you got.
I'll take a picture of
both you guys standing there.
Peter, you get the energy first.
-Pretending like you…
-How long does he have to
stand next to it to get the energy?
No, you know what?
The Miccosukees and Seminoles,
they actually form bands
around these trees.
And because of the energy they have.
Go.
You are communing with
a tree of knowledge.
You can think of it as an ent if you want,
from Lord of the Rings.
Just the point that these things
are incredible creatures.
And when they get cut,
they don't last anymore.
-You and I talked about redwoods.
-Yeah.
The redwoods were preserved by the
Redwoods League, which were evil people.
They were cutting redwoods. Why?
They wouldn't save them
because they were using them for pipes
for waste water and that's before
they had metal pipes.
And also Transcontinental Railroad.
-Oh, you got it.
A lot of California was decimated
because they were mining,
especially Nevada
for things like silver and gold.
Wow, look at the light.
I just love how the light plays.
-I know. That's the thing.
See, that's what I want you to see.
That's nice.
You are doing what I like to do
with people. I bring them out here
and they close their eyes
and it's magic.
You just hear your breath.
You breathe through your nose slowly.
And we have the absence of the traffic.
It's primeval.
It's a fantasy land.
It's a connection.
So when people go to Disney to see
the different hippopotamuses
coming out of the river tour
and all that, I take them to reality.
To try to explain it is very difficult.
The way to understand this
is to experience it.
-Yeah.
And all of the stereotypes
that you brought with you
about the stinking swamp, the quicksand,
there's no quicksand out here,
about the attacking alligators
which we've seen.
All right. All the things.
Back in the '40s, it was the Indians
that would take you out.
Not as a date.
It was a final trip.
So the things that we bring baggage-wise,
I like to remove that baggage
and show you what
the true connections are out here.
-I appreciate it.
And you can be part of that by,
like we just did,
and listen to nothing.
-Which is the best.
-There's everything in the nothingness.
Correct.
[silence]
[Peter] All right.
So here's the legend, Clyde Butcher.
And you said this photography is amazing.
Yeah. You have to see it for yourself.
-Hey, guys.
-Hey, how you doing?
Good. How was the walk?
-So cool.
-Spectacular.
Clyde has been called the Ansel Adams
of the Everglades by some.
He's traditional large-format
black-and-white photography.
Film, prints,
made in the darkroom, handmade.
Each handmade.
[Peter] Oh, that's beautiful.
Wow.
-So, you know, as a photographer too,
Clyde's just such a huge inspiration.
-You're a photographer also?
-Yeah. I have work in here as well.
-This is his wife's work?
-Yep. This is Niky Butcher, his wife.
-And she does some color.
-Yep.
So it's black-and-white photography,
and then she hand-colors it.
Oh, okay. I got you.
Yeah, it's got a surreal look to it.
Very traditional Florida colors,
turquoise and pinks and yellows.
-Okay, that's really interesting.
That's almost 3D. It's like coming to life.
[Harrison] It's unique.
-This is all your work, Andy?
-Yes.
-Nice.
-Wonderful.
Oh, that's a cool one.
Yeah, that was in my head
for a long time, trying to…
Had this thought of a mangrove
with a perfect reflection of a gator.
-You're putting your time in
out there then.
Getting shots like this.
-That is so cool.
-Thank you.
[Harrison] The roseate
with the babies too.
[Peter] I love this.
[Peter] Now we're deep in
on the dirt roads.
[Harrison] Deep in the Cypress.
Turner River Road.
-But a few of these places, huh?
-Yes. And that is, again, the key…
-"Bad dog. He thinks he's a lion."
I bet he does.
That's the key difference
in the designation is that
there's a lot of homestead camps out here
and hunting camps
and people still living out here.
That's a genuine Big Cypress swamp buggy.
Unique vehicles made for this terrain.
And if you see these old pictures
of them in the '20s and '30s,
they'd have like Model A engines
and Model T engines.
A lot of them have the tires
as tall as you and me, you know?
-Oh, nice.
-Look at that thing. For the big Cypress.
-Can we check it out?
-Yeah. Let's pull over and check it out.
This is really interesting, guys.
It's like Uganda.
-Have you been to Uganda?
-I have.
-Looks like this?
-Sort of.
-Some areas.
-Yeah?
Look at this thing.
-Do they have swamp buggies in Uganda?
-I don't think so.
This thing is wild.
Where the airboats can't go
or what's that all about?
Yeah, the water is deeper and more narrow
than the airboats can get through.
And then it also does a good job
of getting through the dryer patches
that the airboats can't get to.
-Oh, yeah.
So it's like specific
for this environment, you know?
[engine rattling]
[Peter] We just saw this buggy
and we're like, it's so beautiful out here.
Someone's got to come back for it.
It's pretty.
-It is.
Where does one buy a buggy like this?
-You don't. You build it.
-You built these?
-Yeah. You build them.
You found like an old truck chassis?
A friend of mine built this one.
Hell, it's 35 years old.
We've rolled it over. We got drunk.
There's been more deer hanging off of this
than most people seen in a lifetime.
-Are you from out here?
I'm from Chokoloskee.
-Born and raised?
-Born and raised.
How's it been?
The earlier life was really better.
Things has changed so much
with the national parks and stuff.
We used to… fly free.
You know, we used to eat
all the game we wanted.
We killed deer.
We killed, ate manatee.
We ate
loggerhead turtles, green turtles.
We ate white ivis is what they call them.
We call them Chokoloskee chickens, curlew.
-We enjoyed ourselves.
-Oh, yeah.
We didn't have no problems with the law.
If anything, we'd kill a deer
and give them some. You know what I mean?
They never mess with us.
Okay. But I mean, it looks
pretty empty out here obviously.
-These parts, especially.
-I don't break the law no more.
-Yeah.
-I don't even drive fast.
I don't… It ain't worth it.
After getting in trouble
and doing the things I done,
you know, I smuggled…
I was part of a family,
part of our family, and we smuggled
millions of pounds of weed.
I did 10 years.
-No way. No way.
I did 10 years in federal prison.
Got my picture in Life Magazine.
You did 10 years in prison
for smuggling weed?
10 years.
So we heard that story from this morning.
-In Copeland.
From Copeland they were talking about
you were running drugs.
Man, the money was just unbelievable.
It was like something off of a TV.
Like thousands and thousands a week.
Hundreds of thousands of dollars.
A month?
Oh, a week.
A day!
-[laughter]
-C'mon!
We had so much money, man,
it was giving it away.
How long did that last for?
About five, six years.
Okay, and then you went to prison
for 10 years.
Yeah.
How was that? I mean you probably
don't want to talk about it.
-It was pretty neat.
-It was pretty neat?
Yeah. I mean,
I went to Eglin Air Force Base.
It's like a Boy Scout camp.
Work out, gym, no fences.
It was pretty neat.
I did half of my time there.
When I got out, I got busted.
I say 10 years.
I got busted for a rifle in my truck
and he give me another five years.
-That wasn't fun.
-Are you serious?
-Yeah. That was serious.
-Oh, man.
Then I did five years in a state prison.
That wasn't fun.
That Florida state prisons.
The federal prisons are way better?
Oh, man. Come on.
That Eglin Air Force Base was like a dream.
I mean, if I would have went
to state prison the very first time,
I'd have never broke another law.
-From what you did before to now this.
This is peaceful now, huh?
-Oh, it's great.
I do tours in
the Big Cypress National Preserve.
I love my job.
-Steve, what were you saying?
We're screwing you up?
Screwing me up. I got sh*t I gotta do.
Come on. Get on. Get on.
All right.
Steve's giving us a little ride here.
I got it. Yeah.
-[Harrison] Can't be mad at that.
-[Peter] Thank you, Steve.
-Appreciate it.
-Those people there loved it.
[Harrison] Where were they from?
Hell, I don't know where they were from.
Let's see how much they loved it.
Gave me a 20.
[Harrison] That's somewhat loved it.
-[Peter] They're paying…
-That's good. That's nice of them.
If they give me $5, it's nice of them.
You know what I mean?
-Yeah.
-I don't…
People work hard for their money.
[engine starts]
I can't…
[Peter] So this is your full-time gig?
This is what you do?
I don't smuggle no more.
This is what I do.
-Less money, less stress.
A lot less money.
-What's it like
when you make that much money?
What does it do to your head?
Makes you think you're invincible.
You can buy everybody off.
When you got that much money,
everybody thinks…
you're the man!
They all want to be around you.
Because you got so much money.
Right.
[Steve] Which is all right? I understand.
You know, and I treated people good.
I found 10 grand in my truck
one day behind the seat.
It was close to Christmas.
I went out and give it all away.
Somebody asked me, said,
you still got my rifle?
I said, I don't know. Let me check
and see if I got a .22 Magnum.
Let me see it might be behind the seat.
When I flipped the seat up,
there was a rolled up paper sack.
I said, what the hell was that?
I opened up. It was $10,000.
That and an ounce of cocaine.
Good cocaine from Miami, right off the key.
So, I went and got me
a bottle of Crown Royal.
Went out to Copeland.
Used to be the Black section and stuff.
We'd build a big fire and threw that
ounce of cocaine on the tailgate
with a bottle of Crown.
And I started handing out
that 10 grand to everybody.
We had a good time.
They had a good Christmas, them folks.
You don't do that stuff anymore?
No sir. I don't even drink.
I don't smoke. I don't drink.
I got a 20-year-old daughter
I raised from a baby.
I didn't have no girlfriends or nothing
because I wanted to raise my daughter.
Oh, that's cool.
So, you've been clean 20 years?
-Oh, longer than that.
-Oh, nice.
I went to work for the park first.
-Right.
You know, they say…
-Can I sit up on this?
-Yeah.
As long as you are clean for 10 years,
and you don't have no violent crimes,
the park will hire you.
A lot of felons work for the park.
-Okay, good.
-So, I was clean.
I was over 10 years.
I've got my rights restored.
I can vote and everything.
So, this whole road right here,
the reason it's built up like this,
is because it goes into
an exploration oil well.
The Big Cypress has oil underneath of it.
There's two or three
active oil wells right now,
down towards Dade County.
It runs all the way up.
It's just south of Immokalee.
The oil line does.
It's called Sunnyland Oil Field.
Runs all the way to Dade County.
-Okay.
It's got it piped
across the prairies down there.
I don't know where the pipeline goes.
It's just crude oil,
making tires and roads and stuff like that.
Hey, I'd take y'all
for a trip tonight and ride you,
but I've got to go get my rear end.
It's my recovery buggy.
I do all the recovery work
for the Big Cypress.
If somebody comes
and gets stuck or something,
I've got to go get them.
And they count on me, you know.
And I don't…
That's my recovery buggy.
It's a Land Rover rear end.
Which Land Rovers are made
for farming and ranching
and stuff like that.
So…
[Peter] Tight community
out here in the Everglades?
-Yeah. Very tight.
Chokoloskee is the main place.
-Okay.
-That's where it happens.
We went to that shop,
that beautiful shop there.
-Smallwood.
-You went to the Smallwood store?
-A couple years ago.
-That's my cousin's place.
I made a video. She was in it.
Lynn.
Lynn was in the video a couple years ago.
That's my cousin.
We got the same granddad.
Do you worry at all about
this culture going away?
-It's going away.
Ain't just worried about it.
It's going away.
What do you mean?
It's…
Everything's tightening it up.
Can't do this. Can't do that.
Can't go here. Can't go there.
It's all changing.
You can jump off and clock
this gate for me if you would.
[Harrison] Yep.
Be careful looking down
at the bottom of that gate.
We've had a big moccasin down there.
I'll wait on you.
Be careful.
I'd spend some time with you, brother, but…
-I appreciate… No, this is very cool.
If he's here tomorrow or something,
we could hang out at the house.
-I appreciate it.
So, Steve, culture's going away.
-What about…
-Culture's going away, brother.
-Always has.
-Are the kids moving out?
Kids don't have… Kids are moving out.
Ain't nothing for them here.
Um…
Everything's changing.
There ain't no more old school.
Ain't no more old ways.
Well, Steve, thank you.
Oh, you're welcome.
For those that want to do this
and get deep in there,
and get the great stories
from you, the local,
how do they find you?
You got to go to Captain Steve's
Swamp Buggy Adventures.
Call my home number.
Leave a message.
If I'm not there, I'll call you back.
But listen, it's the awesomest thing
you've ever done.
If you want to spend a few hours…
Hey, I do nighttime rides.
I do snake hunting trips.
We'll start a campfire and cook your food.
Bring all the kids.
Bring some hot dogs.
We'll do all that.
-I appreciate it. Thank you.
-Thank you, Steve.
Well, thanks, brother.
Thank y'all very much.
-It's so cool.
-Pleasure to meet you.
My son's truck,
he got killed four years ago.
I'm sorry, man.
Like, it killed me, dude.
You ever watch Josh Gates on
Destination Unknown, Destination X?
He had a room with 10 people that had died.
One of them was dead
for 45 minutes in ice water.
Every one of them
said they didn't want to come back.
-Wow.
-Every one of them said the same thing.
"We didn't want to come back.
We died.
We didn't want to come back.
It was so nice
and so beautiful
that we did not want to come back,
that somebody told us
that our time wasn't up,
that we had to come home."
So that makes you feel good,
you know, if you lost somebody like me.
Jesus… God,
is building an army.
You know the world's
going to hell in a handbasket.
You know, you can see it.
I'm not a throwing Christian. I'm not.
I believe. I'm a believer.
But I believe that God is building an army
because I have seen so many
people my son's age die.
He just lost his best friend, same age.
-From what, if you don't mind me asking?
-Just from all different stuff.
My son was killed on a motorcycle.
The other one was killed…
He had um,
uh, gas, gastroentero problems.
But I'm just saying, God's building
an army.
He's building an army
with these young strong people, you know,
because it's gonna come down to it one day.
It's got to.
This world can't keep going
like it's going.
I mean, you got to admit,
things ain't looking good.
Positive note.
Be good.
Be a good person. Treat people right.
Treat people
the way you would like to be treated.
I don't care if you're on drugs.
I don't care if you're an alcoholic.
You can get off it all.
I've been on it all. I've done it all.
I've been a drug addict.
I've sold stuff
just to buy pain pills.
Listen, you can do good.
You can, you can do good.
And money ain't everything.
It ain't about money.
It's about enjoying yourself,
being good to your family.
And I'm being from the heart about that.
That's the way I look at it,
you know, and
save your things.
Like you walk into my living room,
I got old things in there, you know,
stuff from my kids
and pictures all over the walls
and old
posted signs and stuff.
You know, it's not going to be here
in hundreds of years.
So… yeah.
-[Harrison] But the videos will.
-The videos will.
-Steve, good stuff.
-All right. Thank you.
I'll be talking to you.
-All right, Steve.
-I hope, I hope you do good
with that video.
I really do.
[Peter] Well, Harrison, thank you, man.
Very cool day.
Awesome. I'm glad you enjoyed it.
-Glad you enjoyed it.
-Awesome. Loved it.
Yeah, we met a lot of different people.
We unpacked all the different layers.
That was the coolest part about it.
And so, for people wanting this experience,
Harrison's your man.
Harrison can get you in.
We did another video a couple years ago.
Onto the water in his boat.
Yeah.
But more these days, you're on land.
Yes, yes. And I'm happy
to refer to any boat tours.
I have a couple friends
who are captains and can do that.
But as far as knowing
the different spots of the Everglades,
the history, connecting the dots,
meeting all the different personalities
that are out here.
And as far as getting
a lay of the land
and getting a true immersion
into the Everglades,
that's not just the touristy stuff.
-Yeah.
That's what I really specialize in,
you know,
personalized to what you're trying to…
what you're trying to see
and what you're trying to accomplish.
I'm going to leave your, you have a link
of some sort, I'll leave that down below.
Website, Instagram, YouTube,
all up to a bunch of adventures
and just how to, you know,
inspire wilderness
and get to the different corners.
-Get in this. The Florida
you don't know for the most part.
I guarantee 99% of the people
haven't been to this part of the state.
All right, guys. Thanks for coming
on that journey.
Until the next one.
[country music]